Guide to the Berliner Family Papers, 1878-1967
Rauh Jewish Archives
Senator John Heinz History Center
The Berliner Family Papers 1878-1967
Berliner Family
4 (5 boxes)
In 1866, Meyer Berliner, a Jewish tradesman, and his family moved from Wellsville, New York, to Corry, Pennsylvania. The family would become prominent residents of Corry, with three generations operating several different businesses in the town between the 1880s and 1920s. This collection consists of material primarily from the Corry Hide and Fur Company and the Berliner Company, both mail-order hide and fur companies, and the personal correspondence of Lawrence Berliner, a grandson of Meyer Berliner. Through business and personal correspondence, receipts and invoices, market reports, and promotional material, this collection documents the companies’ day-to-day operations as well as the activities of the Berliner family.
Rauh Jewish Archives; Senator John Heinz History Center 1212 Smallman Street Pittsburgh, PA 15222
MSS#297
History
In 1866, Meyer Berliner, a Jewish tradesman, and his family moved from Wellsville, New York, to Corry, Pennsylvania. Along with his son, Jacob, Meyer started a tallow rendering business, M. Berliner & Co., in the late 1880s, which would only last five years before failing. Meyer and Jacob were also organizers of the Ahaveth Sholem Lodge, no.160 Independent Order of B’nai Brith in Corry.
In 1900, five years after the death of Meyer, Jacob and his two sons, Lawrence and Manfred J., launched the Corry Hide and Fur Company, a mail-order hide and fur business with offices located on West Main Street in Corry. The company purchased a variety of furs, skins, and hides from trappers located across North America, often selling the material through representatives based in London and Leipzig, Germany. The company also sold scent lures for trapping, tallow, beeswax, and a guide for trapping. During the summer, when the quality of fur decreased, the company would buy ginseng root from trappers, which would be sold for its medicinal value in Asia.
By 1912, the company was thriving, with a larger warehouse and a force of 15 employees responsible for sending out pricelists and answering correspondence. In January of that year, the company made headlines in a local paper when it sold a silver grey fox skin to a Russian Grand Duchess. During World War I, prices for hides and skins increased, as the demand for leather in Europe grew. The market for furs was more unstable, as the market in Leipzig was shutdown and spending on luxury items decreased.
In 1914, the brothers started the Berliner Leather Company (shortly thereafter known as the Berliner Company), which they billed as the “successors to the Corry Hide and Fur Company,” though for a number of years the two companies seemed to run concurrently. Following the death of Manfred J. Berliner in 1924 at age 43, Lawrence moved with his mother, Emily, to New York City. At some point, Celia and Manfred Jacob Berliner, the wife and son of his late brother, would also relocate to New York City. The Berliner Company’s operations slowed considerably following the move. However, Lawrence Berliner remained active in the industry, becoming a member of the New York Hide Exchange. In the 1930s, Berliner returned to Corry before relocating to Florida with Celia and Manfred Jacob Berliner in the 1940s.
In addition to the family businesses, Lawrence Berliner worked occasionally as a freelance journalist, providing news about Corry and the entertainment industry for a several publications.
Lawrence Berliner passed away on June 29, 1969.
Scope and Content Notes
The records of the Corry Hide and Fur Company are housed in five archival boxes and are arranged in two series. The first series contains business records, consisting mainly of correspondence and invoices, of three Berliner family businesses: M. Berliner and Co. (c.1888-1893), The Corry Hide and Fur Company (c.1900-c.1916), and the Berliner Company (1916-c.1929). Also included in this series are market reports and promotional material from the Corry Hide and Fur Company, auction catalogs from several London auction houses, and market reports published by other companies in the industry. The materials in this series illuminate the day-to-day activities of the Corry Hide and Fur Company/Berliner Company as well as the early 20th century fur and hide industry.
The second series houses personal material from the Berliner family. Consisting mainly of correspondence sent to Lawrence, this series also holds records pertaining to his father Jacob, mother Emily, brother Manfred J., uncle William, nephew Manfred Jacob, and sister-in-law Celia Levene Berliner.
Series I: Berliner Family Business Records, 1888-1947
The bulk of the material in this series consists of correspondence between the Corry Hide and Fur Company/Berliner Company and its trading partners, which included individual trappers, tanneries, other hide and fur businesses. There is also correspondence originating from financial institutions, railroads and newspaper publishers. The correspondence is mostly incoming mail, though there is a small amount of letters originating from the company as well. The correspondence pertains to customer orders (including a number of disagreements over the quality or price of goods), the prices and availability of materials, advertisements placed in publications, and disputes with railroad companies over damaged shipments and overcharges. Some letters that were sent to traders were returned with handwritten responses on the back, providing a glimpse into the interaction between the Berliners and their customers. Additional corporate material includes circulars and copies of advertisements containing pricing information, testimonials, and shipping instructions. Also included in this series are price lists, receipts and invoices, canceled checks, market reports, and auction catalogs that document the fluctuations in the fur and hide market during this time.
Series II: Berliner Family Papers, 1871-1967
This series contains correspondence, receipts, and ephemera from the Berliner family. The bulk of the series consists of correspondence addressed to Lawrence Berliner. The letters concern business activities not officially conducted by Corry Hide and Fur Company or Berliner Company, rental properties owned by Berliner, information regarding stocks, travel arrangements, and numerous complaints made against railroads and other various companies. Some of the correspondence is from periodicals, such as Variety, The Cleveland Plains Dealer, and The Jamestown Morning Post and concerns freelance reporting jobs that Lawrence Berliner undertook, usually covering entertainment news and activities in the Corry area. There is also some correspondence received from family members, including his brother Manfred and his uncle David Taylor of New York. Because the Corry Hide and Fur Company and Berliner Company were family-run businesses, some of what has been classified as personal correspondence also contains information about the family businesses. In particular, letters from Lawrence’s older brother Manfred contain specific instructions to be followed when one was away from the other. These letters also contain candid observation about other businessmen in the industry.
There are much smaller groups of correspondence connected to the other members of the Berliner family. Manfred J. Berliner’s correspondence includes letters from the early car manufacturers Petrel Motor Car and Imperial Automobiles. The correspondence of Emily Berliner (née Taylor), the only other sizeable subgroup of family correspondence in the collection, includes letters from members of the Taylor family.
Among the assorted family documents is an 1875 deed ascribed to Rosalie Berliner and an 1899 summons for William Berliner. Also in the collection is a series of military press releases documenting events in the final months of the Pacific Theater of World War II, though their connection to the creators of the collection remains unclear.
Controlled Access Terms
Personal Names
Berliner, Lawrence; Berliner, Manfred
Corporate Names
M. Berliner and Co. (Corry, Pa.); The Corry Hide and Fur Company (Corry, Pa.); The Berliner Company (Corry, Pa.)
Topics
Jewish businesspeople--Pennsylvania--History--Sources; Jews--Pennsylvania--Pittsburgh; Fur trade--North America--History--20th century
Locations
Corry (Pa.); Erie County (Pa.)
No Restrictions.
Received in two accessions:
Acc# 1996.190; Purchased from the Charles Apfelbaum Company on June 12, 1996.
Acc# 2008.0072; Donated by the Queens Library in February, 2008.
Related Materials
There are photocopies of articles pertaining to the Berliners, which appeared in the Corry Evening Journal between 1906 and 1972, in the Corry Hide and Fur Co. vertical file (Western PA—Erie County—Corry—Corry Hide and Fur Co.). Additional information about the Berliner family and the Corry Hide and Fur Company can be found at the Erie County Historical Society and the Corry Area Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
Separated Materials
One folder of several copies of market report newsletters from the Berliner Company have been separated and described as MSO#297.
- Business Records1888-1947, I:
  The bulk of the material in this series consists of correspondence between the Corry Hide and Fur Company/Berliner Company and its trading partners, which included individual trappers, tanneries, other hide and fur businesses. There is also correspondence originating from financial institutions, railroads and newspaper publishers. The correspondence is mostly incoming mail, though there is a small amount of letters originating from the company as well. The correspondence pertains to customer orders (including a number of disagreements over the quality or price of goods), the prices and availability of materials, advertisements placed in publications, and disputes with railroad companies over damaged shipments and overcharges. Some letters that were sent to traders were returned with handwritten responses on the back, providing a glimpse into the interaction between the Berliners and their customers. Additional corporate material includes circulars and copies of advertisements containing pricing information, testimonials, and shipping instructions. Also included in this series are price lists, receipts and invoices, canceled checks, market reports, and auction catalogs that document the fluctuations in the fur and hide market during this time.
  - M. Berliner and Co.
    - Correspondence1888-1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Receipts1888-1893 (Folder 2)
  - Corry Hide and Fur Company
    - Correspondence
      - 1888-1893 (Folder 3)
      - 1908-1909 (Folder 4)
      - 1910-1911 (Folder 5)
      - 1912 (Folder 6)
      - 1912 (Folder 7)
      - 1913 (Folder 8-10)
      - 1914 (Folder 11-12)
      - 1915 (Folder 13-14)
      - 1916 (Folder 15-16)
      - 1917-1924 (Folder 17)
      - undated (Folder 18)
    - Invoices
      - Invoice ledger "A" 1907 (Volume 1)
      - Invoice ledger "B" 1907-1908 (Volume 2)
      - 1913-1916 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 1916 (Folder 2)
    - Receipts
      - 1903-1916 (Folder 3-5)
      - Pricelistsnd (Folder 6)
      - Promotional materialsnd (Folder 7)
      - Freight Bills1907-1908 (Folder 8)
  - The Berliner Company
    - Correspondence
      - 1914-1916 (Folder 9-10)
      - 1917 (Folder 11-12)
      - 1918 (Folder 13-15)
      - 1919 (Folder 16-17)
      - 1920 (Folder 18-19)
      - 1921 (Folder 20)
      - 1922-1924 (Folder 21-22)
      - 1925-1929 (Folder 23)
      - undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1917-1929 (Folder 2-3)
    - Overcharge/damage against railroads1917-1926 (Folder 4)
    - Account Books1902-1920 (Folder 5)
    - Canceled Checks1886-1930 (Folder 6-8)
    - Ledgers
      - Oil Creek Tannery1892-1899 (Volume 3)
      - 1926-1932 (Folder 9)
  - Fur Industry
    - Auction catalogs
      - A. and W. Nesbitt1915 (Folder 10)
      - Fred K. Huth & Company
        - 1915-1917 (Folder 11)
        - 1918 (Folder 12)
        - 1919 (Folder 13)
      - C.M. Lampson & Company1915-1919 (Folder 13)
      - Unknown auction catalognd (Folder 13)
    - Auction reports1914-1919 (Folder 16)
    - Market Reports1912-1932 (Folder 17)
    - New York Hide Exchange Market Reports1929-1931 (Folder 18)
    - Pamphlets and circulars1902-1947 (Folder 19)
- Berliner Family Papers1871-1967, II:
  This series contains correspondence, receipts, and ephemera from the Berliner family. The bulk of the series consists of correspondence addressed to Lawrence Berliner. The letters concern business activities not officially conducted by Corry Hide and Fur Company or Berliner Company, rental properties owned by Berliner, information regarding stocks, travel arrangements, and numerous complaints made against railroads and other various companies. Some of the correspondence is from periodicals, such as Variety, The Cleveland Plains Dealer, and The Jamestown Morning Post and concerns freelance reporting jobs that Lawrence Berliner undertook, usually covering entertainment news and activities in the Corry area. There is also some correspondence received from family members, including his brother Manfred and his uncle David Taylor of New York. Because the Corry Hide and Fur Company and Berliner Company were family-run businesses, some of what has been classified as personal correspondence also contains information about the family businesses. In particular, letters from Lawrence’s older brother Manfred contain specific instructions to be followed when one was away from the other. These letters also contain candid observation about other businessmen in the industry.
  There are much smaller groups of correspondence connected to the other members of the Berliner family. Manfred J. Berliner’s correspondence includes letters from the early car manufacturers Petrel Motor Car and Imperial Automobiles. The correspondence of Emily Berliner (née Taylor), the only other sizeable subgroup of family correspondence in the collection, includes letters from members of the Taylor family.
  Among the assorted family documents is an 1875 deed ascribed to Rosalie Berliner and an 1899 summons for William Berliner. Also in the collection is a series of military press releases documenting events in the final months of the Pacific Theater of World War II, though their connection to the creators of the collection remains unclear.
  - Lawrence Berliner
    - Correspondence
      - 1897-1919 (Folder 20)
      - 1920-1929 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      - 1930-1949 (Folder 3-4)
      - 1950-1967 (Folder 5)
      - undated (Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous Papers1918-1966 (Folder 7)
      - Receipts1910-1946 (Folder 8)
  - Manfred J. Berliner
    - Correspondence
      - 1892-1915 (Folder 9)
      - 1916-1922 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Family Correspondence
      - Celia Berliner1936-1947 (Folder 2)
      - Emily Berliner1907-1931 (Folder 3)
      - Jacob Berliner 1892-1924 (Folder 4)
      - Manfred Jacob Berliner1930-1960 (Folder 5)
      - William Berliner1896-1921 (Folder 6)
      - Unidentified1893-1940 (Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Berliner family documents1891-1903 (Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous papers1878-1967 (Folder 9)
    - Pamphlets1898-1936 (Folder 10)
    - Press releases from CINCPOA (Commander-In-Chief, Pacific Ocean Area) 1945 (Folder 11)
    - Receipts 1871-1886 (Folder 12)